<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<eml:eml xmlns:eml="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.1 http://rs.gbif.org/schema/eml-gbif-profile/1.1/eml.xsd"
        packageId="2985efd1-45b1-46de-b6db-0465d2834a5a"  system="http://gbif.org" scope="system"
  xml:lang="en">

<dataset>
      <alternateIdentifier>10.15468/rtnb4m</alternateIdentifier>
        <alternateIdentifier>https://collections.ala.org.au/public/show/dr710</alternateIdentifier>
        <alternateIdentifier>511a3d16-66cd-3cae-9d21-60cdc59dec45</alternateIdentifier>
        <alternateIdentifier>http://collections.ala.org.au/public/show/dr710</alternateIdentifier>
        <alternateIdentifier>2985efd1-45b1-46de-b6db-0465d2834a5a</alternateIdentifier>
        <alternateIdentifier>bef76b2c-5926-3b7b-9f21-960c56d0332c</alternateIdentifier>
        <alternateIdentifier>ae74dd39-6920-3011-baf7-26754ebfc4ef</alternateIdentifier>
    <title>Tasmanian Natural Values Atlas</title>
    <creator>
<organizationName>Tasmanian Natural Values Atlas</organizationName>    <address>
<administrativeArea>Tasmania</administrativeArea><country>AUSTRALIA</country>    </address>
<onlineUrl>http://www.dpiw.tas.gov.au/inter.nsf/webpages/ljem-6tv6tv?open</onlineUrl>    </creator>
    <metadataProvider>
<organizationName>Tasmanian Natural Values Atlas</organizationName>    <address>
<administrativeArea>Tasmania</administrativeArea><country>AUSTRALIA</country>    </address>
<onlineUrl>http://www.dpiw.tas.gov.au/inter.nsf/webpages/ljem-6tv6tv?open</onlineUrl>    </metadataProvider>
    <associatedParty>
<organizationName>Atlas of Living Australia</organizationName>    <address>
<deliveryPoint>CSIRO Ecosystems Services</deliveryPoint><city>Canberra</city><administrativeArea>ACT</administrativeArea><postalCode>2601</postalCode><country>AUSTRALIA</country>    </address>
<electronicMailAddress>info@ala.org.au</electronicMailAddress>    <role>DISTRIBUTOR</role>
    </associatedParty>
      <pubDate>
      2019-10-11
      </pubDate>
    <language>ENGLISH</language>
    <abstract>
        <para>ABOUT THE NATURAL VALUES ATLAS
The Natural Values Atlas provides an easy to use web interface allowing access to authoritative and comprehensive natural values information.  It draws together in one centralised location data on Tasmanian flora and fauna including Threatened species and weeds as well as the Tasmanian Geodiversity Database.  It also incorporates access to other essential data sets such as TASVEG, Threatened communities and Reserves.  The Natural Values Atlas is a supported information tool that ensures knowledge about Tasmania&amp;#39;s valuable natural assets is readily available and quickly obtained.  This information informs planning and decision making processes across all levels of government, industry and the general public, assisting to improve conservation outcomes for natural values in the State.

SPECIES
The Natural Values Atlas is comprised of a database and web based application that allows observations of plants and animals from various sources to be viewed, recorded and analysed.  It can be used to search for information on more than 20,000 plant and animal species from Tasmania, Australia and can display maps showing their location and extent.  There are currently over 1 million observations of plants and animals recorded in the Natural Values Atlas which have been collected by a variety of custodians.  This information has been generated through general species surveys and projects undertaken for scientific research, environmental assessments and other purposes throughout the State since the 1800&amp;#39;s.
The application maintains species taxonomy, attributes and conservation values and provides access to images, related web sites and management documents such as listing statements and recovery plans.  Habitat Mapping for a number of high priority threatened fauna species is also available.  Information sourced from monitoring individual flora and fauna species is accessible as well as samples and analysis which allows information about samples that are associated with an observation to be recorded and tracked.

GEODIVERSITY
The Natural Values Atlas can be used to find and download information about sites that are listed in the Tasmanian Geodiversty Database either for their geology, geomorphology or soil conservation values.  The database contains descriptions of the sites and the geodiverstiy values they encompass, their significance to conservation, sensitivity to disturbance, and advice as to appropriate site management.  The Natural Values Atlas can display maps showing the location and extent of sites.

MANAGEMENT
Management locations and activities are another important area of the Natural Values Atlas which provide access to data about locations where activities are being undertaken to control, monitor, manage or maintain natural values.  Examples include 1080 baits, traps, nests, nest boxes and monitoring plots.

PROJECTS
All data stored in the Natural Values Atlas is organised under a Project.  This component of the Natural Values Atlas contains information regarding the custodian responsible for the project, specific project details such as the people involved in the project or the methodology used to collect the data.  Associated reports, links and images can also be found in this area.  It provides metadata for each project data set.

CONSEVATION INFORMATION SYSTEM
The Conservation Information System (CIS) contains data that assists with conservation planning at the landscape scale.  The CIS Conservation Analysis interface allows you to apply your own weightings for a particular conservation value to create a map of areas that have a high density of the natural values of interest.

NATURAL VALUES REPORTS
Natural Values Reports enables multiple data sets to be brought together in the one report providing a resource that can be used for desktop assessments of natural values for specific areas.  Some of the data sets available through the Natural Values Report facility include: threatened species, species of conservation significance, weeds, geodiversity, TASVEG, threatened communities and reserves.

QUALITY ASSURANCE
New data is loaded into the Natural Values Atlas daily and existing data is regularly reviewed and updated as required.  All data in the Natural Values Atlas is carefully scrutinized by the NVA team who draw on the support of relevant experts to ensure that the data is of the highest quality possible.  This is an ongoing task for which the NVA team welcomes feedback and input from NVA users to continually improve the quality of the data.
The NVA is supported by Metadata and Business Rules.  These are available from within the NVA or on request.
The Natural Values Atlas undergoes constant review and improvement where existing functionality is streamlined and new functionality is added as required.  New versions are regularly released.  The Natural Values Atlas Message Board informs users of changes to the system.

SUPPORT
There is online help embedded in the Natural Values Atlas which instructs users on how to operate the database and make use of the various functions available.  It you are interested in attending a training session then please contact the NVA team to find out what is available.  

HOW TO ACCESS THE NATURAL VALUES ATLAS
Go to www.naturalvaluesatlas.tas.gov.au and select the Register button.  Fill in and submit the form.  You will be informed via email when your user name and password has been activated.  Simplified data from the NVA is also available via the Land Information System Tasmania (LIST) at www.thelist.tas.gov.au.

FURTHER INFORMATION
For enquiries please contact support(at)naturalvaluesatlas.tas.gov.au.</para>
    </abstract>
      <additionalInfo>
          <para>The Natural Values Atlas does contain restricted data however only non restricted project and species observation data will be provided to the ALA. To request access to these records please contact support(at)naturalvaluesatlas.tas.gov.au.</para>
      </additionalInfo>
      <intellectualRights>
        <para>This work is licensed under a <ulink url="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/legalcode"><citetitle>Creative Commons Attribution (CC-BY) 4.0 License</citetitle></ulink>.</para>
      </intellectualRights>
      <distribution scope="document">
          <online>
              <url function="information">https://collections.ala.org.au/public/show/dr710</url>
          </online>
      </distribution>
      <contact>
<organizationName>Atlas of Living Australia</organizationName>    <address>
<deliveryPoint>CSIRO Ecosystems Services</deliveryPoint><city>Canberra</city><administrativeArea>ACT</administrativeArea><postalCode>2601</postalCode><country>AUSTRALIA</country>    </address>
<electronicMailAddress>info@ala.org.au</electronicMailAddress>      </contact>
      <methods>
      </methods>

</dataset>

<additionalMetadata>
    <metadata>
      <gbif>
        <dateStamp>2020-06-15T16:12:43Z</dateStamp>
      <citation>Tasmanian Department of Primary Industries, Parks, Water and Environment (2019). Tasmanian Natural Values Atlas. Occurrence dataset https://doi.org/10.15468/rtnb4m accessed via GBIF.org on 2020-06-15.</citation>
        </gbif>
    </metadata>
</additionalMetadata>

</eml:eml>
